{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In the aftermath of this event, the British government allowed the Kindertransport program to be set up by the Refugee Children’s Movement. A speech noting that demonstrations “should not be prepared or organized” but “are not to be hampered” helped fuel this event, which was triggered after Herschel Grynszpan assassinated diplomat Ernst vom Rath. SA Brownshirts carried out, for ten points, what massive attack on the night of November 9, 1938 against Jewish stores and synagogues in Germany?",
      "answer": "Kristallnacht or the Night of Broken Glass"
    },
    {
      "question": "After this complex was sacked by Chams, it was replaced in function by the nearby Bayon. This complex is the site of a bas-relief showing Vasuki being pulled by 92 asuras and 88 devas in the “Churning of the Sea of Milk.” This complex was built to resemble Mount Meru and dedicated to Vishnu as a Hindu temple by Suryavarman II, but was later transformed into a Buddhist temple. For ten points, name this Khmer temple complex in Cambodia.",
      "answer": "Angkor Wat"
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1869 Supreme Court case involving this state held that its bond sales during the Civil War were invalid. The Gun Free School Zones Act was ruled unconstitutional in a case arising from this state, US v. Lopez. The Supreme Court overturned Bowers v. Hardwick in a 2003 case that struck down this state’s anti-sodomy laws. Abigail Fisher challenged the affirmative action program of, for ten points, what state that admits the top ten percent of each of its high school’s students to its main campus in Austin?",
      "answer": [
        "Texas",
        "Texas v. White",
        "Lawrence v. Texas after “Bowers” is read",
        "Fisher v. University of Texas after “Abigail” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this country, independence leader and human rights activist Hannah Kudjoe created an anti-nudity campaign and distributed clothes. Operation Cold Chop deposed a ruler of this country who was part of the Big Six and founded the Convention People’s Party. The “Motion of Destiny” speech called for the independence of this nation, where the Akosombo dam was built on the Volta River by Kwame Nkrumah. The British colony of Gold Coast controlled what is now, for ten points, what West African country governed from Accra?",
      "answer": "Ghana"
    },
    {
      "question": "Duringthiswar,agroupofsoldiersunderThomasWheelerwereambushedandbesiegedatBrookfield. This war erupted after a group of men were hung for their supposed role in the murder of John Sassamon. The Great Swamp Fight occurred in this war, during which one side was led by the chieftain Metacomet. The Wampanoag fought against colonists in New England in, for ten points, what 17th century war named after a royal moniker? ANSWER:King Philip’sWar(acceptFirst IndianWar;acceptMetacomet’sWarbefore“Metacomet” is read; accept rebellion and other equivalent terms for war) (6) One of these animals is shown carried on someone’s shoulders in the Catacombs of Priscilla. The bottom-central panel of a Van Eyck work shows one of these animals circled by angels and bleeding into a goblet, known as the Adoration of a Mystic one of these animals. This animal symbolizes Jesus’ sacrifice in the Ghent Altarpiece’s depiction of the Agnus Dei. For ten points, name this herd animal that is often shown in artistic depictions of the Good Shepherd.",
      "answer": [
        "lambs or sheep",
        "Agnus Dei before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler forced Catus Decianus to flee to Gaul after a decisive victory at Great Wratting. This ruler defeated Quintus Cerialis at Camulodunum after launching a campaign in response to Roman refusal to honor the will of Prasutagus, but the eventual arrival of Suetonius led to this ruler’s defeat at Watling Street near Londinium. The Nero-era revolt of the Iceni was led by, for ten points, what queen who fought the Romans over control of Britain in AD 60?",
      "answer": "Boudica"
    },
    {
      "question": "This state’s Barataria Nature Reserve and Chalmette Battlefield are administered together as part of the Jean Lafitte National Historical Park. A so-called “country” in this state, centered around the Atchafalaya River and the city of Lafayette, was settled by French speakers who were removed from present-day Nova Scotia in the Great Expulsion. Cajuns settled in, for ten points, what state that contains the Mississippi River Delta and was the site of the 1815 Battle of New Orleans?",
      "answer": "Louisiana"
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician dueled fellow state representative Humphrey Marshall after a spat regarding British cloth. As Speaker, this man succeeded in convincing Southern representatives to adopt the Thomas Proviso, while also convincing Northern representatives to allow Missouri’s admission into the Union as a slave state. This coiner of the term “American System” negotiated a “corrupt bargain” that resulted in John Quincy Adams’ elevation to the presidency. For ten points, name this Kentucky politician known as the Great Compromiser.",
      "answer": "Henry Clay"
    },
    {
      "question": "This leader was embroiled in scandal after his wife was linked to a super-nationalistic kindergarten. This man proposed a new holiday, Restoration of Sovereignty Day, first celebrated in 2013. This leader planned an increase in the consumption tax as part of the Three Arrows, his signature economic plan. This leader rules in partnership with the Komeito Party and succeeded Junichiro Koizumi in his current post. For ten points name this current prime minister of Japan.",
      "answer": "Shinzo Abe , but be lenient"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This ruler launched a military intervention to support John Zapolya against his rival Ferdinand I. Though this ruler signed the Treaty of Amasya to end an inconclusive war with the Safavid Empire, he was more successful in forcing the Knights Hospitaller out of Rhodes to gain control of the Mediterranean. This ruler was victorious at the Battle of Mohacs [moh-hotch] over Louis II of Hungary while expanding into Europe. For ten points, name this longest reigning Ottoman sultan, known as “the Magnificent.”",
        "answer": "Suleiman the Magnificent or Suleiman I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Suleiman’s campaigns were aided by this red bearded Ottoman admiral, who was victorious at the Battle of Preveza against the Holy League but lost Tunis to Charles V.",
        "answer": "Hayreddin Barbarossa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This author bolstered the reputation of Florida as a tourist destination through a book of letters titled Palmetto Leaves. This author was a close friend and travel companion of Elizabeth Campbell, the Duchess of Argyll. This author, who painted an unflattering portrait of Aaron Burr in The Minister’s Wooing, also wrote a novel in which Eva St. Clair urges those around her to convert to Christianity and Simon Legree orders one of his slaves to be beaten to death. For ten points, name this author of Uncle Tom’s Cabin.",
        "answer": "Harriet Beecher Stowe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Stowe’s novel Dred is subtitled “A Tale of” this location, where a community of escaped slaves thrived in the early 19th century. This marshy area stretches from Norfolk in Virginia south to Edenton in North Carolina.",
        "answer": "Great Dismal Swamp"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man ordered the death penalty to be carried out on a man who had destroyed his own frontal lobe, Ricky Ray Rector. One of this man’s failed investments led to Jim and Susan McDougal being investigated by independent counsel Kenneth Starr. Proceedings in a lawsuit filed by Paula Jones against this man were cited in charges of perjury and obstruction of justice brought before the Senate in 1999. For ten points, name this politician whose sexual misconduct led to the second Presidential impeachment trial in history.",
        "answer": [
          "William Jefferson “Bill” Clinton",
          "William Jefferson Blythe"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Bill Clinton’s investments in the Madison Guaranty Savings and Loan, owned by the McDougals, concerned this failed Arkansas land development project, which names the ensuing scandal.",
        "answer": [
          "Whitewater Development Corporation",
          "any additional information that mentions Whitewater"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country was divided into a grid by Raoul Salan’s quadrillage system during its war of independence. The Oran Massacre began in this country on its independence day, and was used as justification by Jean Bastien-Thiry to attempt the assassination of Charles de Gaulle. Ahmed Ben Bella led the FLN in this country, which signed the Evian Accords to gain independence. For ten points, name this former French colony in North Africa.",
        "answer": "Algeria"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This term, from the French for “black foot,” was used to describe Algerians of European descent, most of whom emigrated back to Europe after Algerian independence.",
        "answer": "pied-noirs"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One composer from this country used time signatures like 5/2 and 2/1 [five-two and two-one] for an overture based on the Obhikod liturgical chants. The works of Viktor Hartmann inspired another composer from this country to write a suite whose final movement depicts an unbuilt celebratory gate. C´esar Cui joined those two composers in the “Mighty Handful,” a group of five composers that celebrated this country’s music. For ten points, name this country where Pictures at an Exhibition was composed by Modest Mussorgsky and edited by Nikolai Rimsky-Korsakov.",
        "answer": "Russia"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In addition to the aforementioned Cui, Mussorgsky, and Rimsky-Korsakov, this other member of the Mighty Handful wrote the “musical tableaux” In The Steppes of Central Asia for the silver jubilee of Alexander II, as well as the unfinished opera Prince Igor.",
        "answer": "Alexander Borodin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Members of this family forged the Privilegium Maius. A member of this family became King of the Romans after beating his rival Ottokar II of Bohemia. A severe jaw deformation was present among many members of this family, a genetic defect caused by numerous inter-marriages. The 1713 Pragmatic Sanction was created by this family, whose members included Philip II and Maria Theresa. For ten points, name this European house, originally from Austria, that once ruled Spain and the Holy Roman Empire.",
        "answer": "House of Habsburg or House of Hapsburg"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 1713 Pragmatic Sanction tried to ensure that Maria Theresa would succeed this Holy Roman Emperor. When this man died, France, Bavaria, and Prussia ignored the Pragmatic Sanction and attacked Austria.",
        "answer": "Charles VI, Holy Roman Emperor"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Description acceptable. Alvin Plantinga’s “reformed epistemology” relates the idea of philosophical “warrant” to this idea. Descartes [day-kart] posited that “clear and distinct ideas” must be true because of this idea. Teleological arguments for this idea include the watchmaker analogy. Saint Anselm of Canterbury first laid out the ontological argument for this position, which is often debated against by invoking the problem of evil. For ten points, name this philosophical position that is rejected by atheists.",
        "answer": [
          "the existence of God",
          "answers describing that there is a God, the Christian God in particular",
          "answers describing that one",
          "more gods exist"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This argument, which seemingly demonstrates the logical necessity of believing in a god, was first described in Pens´ees, a work posthumously published in 1670.",
        "answer": "Blaise Pascal’s Wager"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A speech given by this man claims that, though Cassius Clay could also sing, it was swinging that made him a world champion. In 2010, Thomas Hagan was formally paroled for his murder of this man, who gave the “Ballot or the Bullet” speech in 1964. This man took the name name Detroit Red as a criminal; while imprisoned for robbery, he adopted the teachings of Elijah Muhammad. For ten points, name this civil rights activist and member of Nation of Islam who replaced his given surname Little with a single letter.",
        "answer": "Malcolm X"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Malcolm X and Elijah Muhammad both taught this current leader of the Nation of Islam, who organized the Million Man March on Washington in 1995.",
        "answer": [
          "Louis Farrakhan",
          "Louis Walcott"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Prohibition",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Constitutional Amendment that instituted prohibition of alcohol.",
          "answer": "18th Amendment to the US Constitution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Constitutional Amendment that repealed prohibition.",
          "answer": "21st Amendment to the US Constitution."
        },
        {
          "question": "Movement, the “T” in WCTU, that advocated for prohibition.",
          "answer": [
            "temperance",
            "word forms",
            "Women’s Christian Temperance Movement"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "“Hatchet woman” whose bar-smashing tactics earned her dozens of arrests.",
          "answer": "Carrie A. Nation"
        },
        {
          "question": "1919 Congressional act that legislated prohibition once it became constitutional law.",
          "answer": "Volstead Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Investigator who led the Untouchables and took down Al Capone in Chicago.",
          "answer": "Eliot Ness"
        },
        {
          "question": "State where mayor Neal Dow spearheaded prohibition in the 19th century.",
          "answer": "Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lobbyist and leader of the Anti-Saloon League who innovated “pressure politics.”",
          "answer": "Wayne Wheeler"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "English Edwards",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country north of England that gave Edward I his nickname and whose army was later led by William Wallace.",
          "answer": "Scotland"
        },
        {
          "question": "English king who fathered Edward VI with Jane Seymour, one of his six wives.",
          "answer": "Henry VIII"
        },
        {
          "question": "London church where Edward II knighted over 200 men in the Feast of the Swans, and where all English monarchs have been crowned since 1066.",
          "answer": [
            "Westminster Abbey",
            "Collegiate Church of St. Peter at Westminster"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern ruling house of England whose first monarch was Edward VII.",
          "answer": "House of Windsor"
        },
        {
          "question": "English prince who won at Crecy and Poitiers [pwa-tee-ay] during the Hundred Years’ War.",
          "answer": "Edward the Black Prince or Edward of Woodstock"
        },
        {
          "question": "King who imprisoned princes Edward V and Richard of Shrewsbury in the Tower of London in 1483.",
          "answer": "Richard III"
        },
        {
          "question": "American woman for whose love Edward VIII [8] abdicated the throne.",
          "answer": [
            "Wallis Simpson",
            "Wallis Spencer",
            "Bessie Wallis Warfield"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "English nobleman who was defeated by the future Edward I at Evesham after he overthrew Henry III.",
          "answer": "Simon de Montfort"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Scramble for Africa",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "German capital city where an 1884 conference attempted to organize the Scramble.",
          "answer": "Berlin Conference"
        },
        {
          "question": "German chancellor who proposed that 1884 conference.",
          "answer": "Otto von Bismarck"
        },
        {
          "question": "South African empire that fought the battles of Rorke’s Drift, Ulundi, and Isandlwana against the British.",
          "answer": [
            "Zulu Empire",
            "Zululand",
            "amaZulu"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern African country that defeated Italy at Adowa to win its independence.",
          "answer": "Ethiopia"
        },
        {
          "question": "US protectorate country on the Atlantic coast that remained independent during the Scramble.",
          "answer": "Liberia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Belgian king who personally owned the Congo Free State.",
          "answer": "Leopold II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose “Pink Map” proposed a linking of its African colonies.",
          "answer": "Portugal"
        },
        {
          "question": "1898 incident that nearly led to war in Southern Sudan between Britain and France.",
          "answer": "Fashoda Crisis Incident, etc."
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these events ended after Mike Jones was barely able to stop Kevin Dyson. In the aftermath of one of these events, Trent Dilfer was non-traditionally picked for an ad campaign instead of a man arrested for murder the prior year, (20 pts)",
        "Ray Lewis. Malcolm Butler secured a victory in one of these events by intercepting (10 pts)",
        "Russell Wilson, and in 2017, a 28 to 3 lead was blown, causing Atlanta’s second loss in this event. The Vince Lombardi Trophy is awarded to the winners of, for ten points, what championship game of the National Football League?"
      ],
      "answer": "Super Bowls"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One of these systems known as FLOW-MATIC was invented for laypeople by Grace Hopper. Alonzo Church’s lambda calculus serves as the basis for “functional” examples of these constructs, such as Haskell. As depicted in (20 pts)",
        "Hidden Figures, NASA’s Dorothy Vaughn became an expert in one of these constructs known as Fortran. Microsoft’s first product was Altair, an interpreter for one of these constructs named (10 pts)",
        "BASIC. Java, C, and Python are examples of, for ten points, what systems used to write source code, the instructions for a computer program?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "computer programming languages",
        "other additional information"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Oster Conspiracy was planned in case this meeting failed to prevent the launch of Operation Green. A letter denouncing this meeting noted that the country was “offered a choice between war and shame. She has chosen shame and will get war.” (20 pts)",
        "Edvard Benes resigned over this meeting, which resulted in the First Vienna Award. This meeting was proclaimed to have secured (10 pts)",
        "“peace for our time” by Neville Chamberlain. For ten points, name this 1938 meeting in which the Allies appeased Germany by allowing Hitler to annex the Sudetenland."
      ],
      "answer": "Munich Conference"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Troops from this country captured the city of Dire Dawa from this country’s western neighbor; this country was led by Siad Barre during that battle in the Ogaden War. In the early 20th century, the “Mad (20 pts)",
        "Mullah” founded a Dervish state in what is now this country, near where the Majeerteen sultanates had earlier ruled from Puntland. In 1993, when the US invaded this country’s capital to fight Mohamed Farah Aidid, two (10 pts)",
        "Black Hawk helicopters were shot down. For ten points, name this country on the Horn of Africa where the Battle of Mogadishu took place."
      ],
      "answer": "Somalia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Enemy forces were removed from one of these regions in Operation Hastings, which used the Rockpile as an observation post; that one of these regions was north of the Khe Sanh Combat Base in Vietnam. When Arthur Bonifas and Mark Barrett were killed in another of these regions, US forces responded with Operation (20 pts)",
        "Paul Bunyan, the heavily supported cutting of a poplar tree that was supposedly planted by Kim Il-Sung. (10 pts)",
        "Panmunjom and a Joint Security Area are located in one of these areas along the 38th Parallel between North and South Korea. For ten points, give this term for buffer territory between hostile countries where military personnel are banned. ANSWER:Demilitarized Zone(acceptDMZ;acceptVietnameseDemilitarized Zone;acceptKorean Demilitarized Zone after “Arthur Bonifas” is read) (6) This man asserted he was the rightful ruler of his country in a letter to Pope John XXII [22], the Declaration of Arbroath. The Earl of Pembroke was ordered to hunt down this man, handing him a disastrous loss at Methven. This king was (+) excommunicated after murdering John Comyn at the church of the Greyfriars. This man besieged (*) Stirling Castle, forcing the Battle of Bannockburn. For ten points, name this victorious king of the First War of Scottish Independence."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Robert I",
        "Robert the Bruce"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Three years after it was decided, the verdict in this Supreme Court case was used to justify the closing of an educational facility in Richmond, Georgia in Cumming v. School Board. This case was decided 7-1 over John Marshall (20 pts)",
        "Harlan’s dissent, which originated the concept of constitutional colorblindness. Albion Tourge´e [tour-zhay] represented the plaintiff of this case, a one-eighth (10 pts)",
        "black man sponsored by a New Orleans citizens’ committee to ride in a whites-only train car. For ten points, name this 1896 case that established the “separate but equal” doctrine."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Plessy v. Ferguson",
        "either",
        "both underlined portions"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) As part of this movement, Thomas Campbell and his son Alexander founded a sect called the Disciples of Christ. A massive log hall was built in Cane Ridge, (20 pts)",
        "Kentucky by the followers of Barton Stone to house a camp meeting during this movement. The so-called “burned-over district” referred to areas saturated by (10 pts)",
        "Baptist and Methodist converts during this movement. For ten points, identify this Christian revival in early 19th-Century America, so named because it followed a similar movement in the mid-1700s."
      ],
      "answer": "Second Great Awakening"
    }
  ]
}